You all must have heard the news that
Cashless Everywhere or Cashless Anyway both have the
same meaning, so what does it mean? Does it
mean that you can
go to any hospital and get treatment anywhere?
Cashless network has no meaning anymore. It
means that every insurance company has a
cashless network tie-up list, so
apart from that, if you
want to go to any hospital of your choice, you can get treatment there. In
a way, this is what it means, but we will
understand in detail what Cashless Anywhere
means, what is
excluded, what is included in it
and how do you have to proceed
for Cashless Anyway. So, we will
talk about it in detail in this video. Stay till the end of the video, the
video is going to be very useful for you. Before starting the video,
I would like to introduce myself.
My name is Gurleen Kaur Tikku.
I am a Certified Financial Planner. I have been
associated with the insurance industry for the last 18 years and every week I
bring videos for you so that your
personal financial life can become easy and happy
because our company  The tagline of the
same is Creating a Wealth of Happiness. Let's
move on to the video: Cashless Anywhere
or Cashless Everywhere. As you know,
whenever you take a health insurance policy,
every health insurance company has a tie-up
with some hospitals where
you can get treatment cashless. Otherwise,
what you have to do is you have to get reimbursement. The
survey also says that
63% of the claims are settled and 37% of the claims are
settled because
they get treatment outside the network.
Many times, there is no
cashless network hospital available in your area
or the hospital where your doctor is located is
not cashless. Many times, you have to get
treatment done from your doctor only,
but the hospital where he will treat you
may not be in the cashless network. So,
this challenge arises and you have to
file for claim reimbursement. The General
Insurance Council and IRDA together
announced that cashless anywhere is
applicable to all your insurance policies.
So, gradually you will see  Every insurance
company is intimating its policy holders
that you can choose cashless anywhere,
meaning you can
choose cashless treatment anywhere. But there is a system for it, there is
a process for it. If we
talk about it, then this is going to be a huge benefit. Firstly, there will be
convenience
and it will become very smooth. Those who are afraid of claims
that claims are not settled or it will
not be cashless, there is no hospital in my network,
in a tier-to-tier city, there is no hospital there, then what should I do,
for them this is a huge response, a
huge solution. Secondly,
another thing has been seen here which is insurance
penetration, for example, in India it is very low,
only 4 people have insurance
policies, so what will happen with this, there will be
more confidence in insurance and more people will
take insurance policies because cashless
insurance is a big step.
You will get coverage in 40 to 1000 hospitals pan India,
where you will see that every insurance
company has its own list of 7000
hospitals, 10000 hospitals.  12000 hospitals,
15000 and so on. So here you are
getting access to 40000 hospitals by
Cashless Anyway. So what is the literal meaning of Cashless Anyway? The
literal meaning is that
you can go to any hospital and get treatment,
whether it is in the network or not. If it is
in the network, then of course you
can avail cashless treatment. If it is not in the network and
you want to go to that hospital for
treatment, then you can avail cashless treatment. The
hospital should fulfill the definition of a provided hospital. So what is the definition of a hospital?
If that hospital has more than 15 beds, then it will
come under the definition of a hospital. The hospital should be registered
with the state health authorities
under the Clinical Establishment Act. If this is
fulfilled, then that hospital
can provide you cashless facility under Cashless
Anyway. One thing you have to be very careful about is that the
hospital you are going to should
not be a blacklisted hospital. It should
not be an excluded provider. Every
insurance company publishes its list
on its website.  Which is called
blacklisted hospitals or excluded
providers, we had also put a detailed video about it
on our channel last month, you
can refer to that, I will put its link below,
it means that if you
go to those hospitals, we will
not pay you the cost of treatment, we will not give you reimbursement at all
and of course will not provide cashless facility as well,
so you should
not go to blacklisted and excluded providers,
this thing has to be kept in mind, so what will be its process, its
process is quite simple,
if you are getting a planned surgery done, it
is an elective surgery, you are getting a surgery done on your own will
and you know in advance that
you have to get this surgery done, then you are getting it done
in a hospital which is not in the cashless network, then
you have to communicate to the insurance company through email
or talk to the customer support,
tell them that I am
taking this treatment and
I want cashless facility at so and so
hospital and this has to be done 48 hours before
your admission to the hospital, 48 hours before going to the hospital
Before going to
the hospital, you have to intimate the
insurance company, only then they will be
able to arrange cashless facility in that hospital. And if any
such circumstance arises that you have to be
admitted in an emergency, then after
admission, you have to
intimate the insurance company 24 hours that
I want to take cashless facility and the
insurance company will facilitate it. I
would like to mention one more point here, it is
important that the hospital accepts the cashless facility.
Many times it will happen that the
hospital will refuse saying that we will not accept cashless facility,
you make the payment to us and you can
apply for reimbursement. The hospital
is cooperating and it
is accepting the cashless facility, cashless anywhere, then the
insurance company cannot refuse.
You have fulfilled both these conditions provided to make cashless facility available to you
and they will not charge you any additional premium for this facility. The
insurance company will
pay the same insurance premium that you were paying
and the claim will of course be settled as per your policy
terms and conditions.  Your
waiting periods are for the
initial waiting period for slow-growing illnesses and for pre-
existing diseases, so the
claim will be settled as per the policy terms and conditions.
Just for your convenience,
Cashless Anyway has been introduced.
So let us understand in summary
what will be the benefit of Cashless Anyway.
Firstly, you will get convenience. You can get treatment in
any hospital of your choice.
If there is no cashless network there, then
you can get treatment in that hospital.
Secondly, if your doctor
treats you in a specific hospital and that is
not a cashless one, then you get the flexibility to
avail cashless facility there. Thirdly, the
insurance company has millions of policy holders.
All the insurance companies are
talking about health insurance and we are
talking about general insurance, so
they are getting additional hospital list.
Currently, they had access to only 7000 to
10000 hospitals or maximum 15000 hospitals,
now they have it.  There is access to 40,000 hospitals
where they can get treatment.
Another thing that is going to happen is that with cashless
anyway, fraudulent claims will be made. It has been
seen many times that the fraudulent
claims filed are included
in reimbursement and not in cashless. Because
in cashless, many times the insurance company
also sends its investigation officer and
checks whether the patient
is actually admitted or not, what treatment is being
given and so on. Fraudulent
claims generally used to be included in reimbursement. Now
what will happen with this is that reimbursement claims will become
cashless claims. The cost
of the insurance company will also reduce, customer
's inconvenience will reduce and fraudulent
claims will also reduce. So it is a very
good move for everyone. It is a win-win
situation. You just have to keep three things in mind:
first, you have to inform the insurance company 48 hours in advance
that you are
going to some other hospital where you
want to avail cashless facility. Second,
You have to keep in mind that it should
not be a blacklisted hospital, it should
not be an excluded provider, thirdly,
if a hospital is accepting the facility, the
hospital is saying that we will take cashless, then the
insurance company will settle your
claim in cashless, so this was about cashless any where,
cashless everywhere, I am sure
this is going to be very useful
for all the policy holders, you people used to have the same
question that there is no cashless hospital of this company in my network, so the
solution to that problem has been
introduced here and you will
see in future that many things will be standardized, there will be
no insurance company specific, many things are going to be standardized,
new things are going to come,
you will hear about health claim exchange
in the coming time, we will bring a detailed video on that too, it will be
launched soon, that too
in 15 to 20 days, you will hear
some news about that, that is also a good initiative
and many things are going to change
in insurance and yes, if you have taken any claim,
cashless any  Through where or everywhere
and if you want to share your experience,
please share it, it will help other people
who are watching this video and
before leaving, a quick reminder, if
you have not yet subscribed to our channel, do it so that you get the
right
information at the right time, we will meet you
in the next video with a new topic, till then
stay safe and take care, bye bye